Inventory of the Roland W. Brown papers, 1919-1979
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Roland W. Brown papers
1919-1979
Brown, Roland W., 1897-1989
04459
1.43 cubic ft. (5 containers)
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Materials about Roland W. Brown, the Brown Family, the Teton Valley, and the University of Wyoming.
Biography of Roland W. Brown
Roland W. Brown was born June 12, 1897 in Providence, Utah. In 1898, Brown’s father became the first U.S. Forest Ranger in Jackson Hole, Wyoming and later in Teton Valley. Brown grew up in Teton Valley and was one of the first 8th grade graduates of the Alta, Wyoming school in 1914, subsequently graduating from Teton High School in 1918. He attended the University of Wyoming during the summers from 1919 to 1923 and Albion State Normal School the summers of 1924 and 1925. For the next five years, he was a teacher and school principal at schools in Teton Valley and Jackson Hole. In 1924, his booklet, Souvenir History of Jackson Hole, was published, featuring S.N. Leek’s photographs of Jackson Hole. Brown homesteaded acreage in Teton Valley during his teaching career and, after his teaching career, worked in sales. In 1931, he married Hattie Wainwright (1901-1993). In 1938, Brown became an agent for the Beneficial Life Insurance Company in their Rexburg, Idaho office, where he was employed for more than 40 years. He, his wife, and two daughters traveled extensively in the United States, Europe, Canada, and Mexico. Brown kept notes of their experiences and turned them into travelogues published by local newspapers. Brown and his family were active members of the LDS Church in their region.
Scope and Content
The Roland W. Brown papers contain biographical materials about Roland W. Brown and family (1919 – 1979), photographs, histories, and promotional materials about Jackson, Wyoming (1919 – 1967), newspaper articles about and histories of Teton Valley (1970 – 1980), tourism brochures and newspaper articles about Wyoming towns and scenic areas (1919 – 1972), and University of Wyoming Summer School bulletins, programs, photographs and other materials (1919 – 1920).
Access Restrictions
The collection is open to the public. The original panoramic photograph can be accessed only with an archivist's permission due to fragility.
Related Materials
There are no known other archival collections created by Roland W. Brown at the date of processing.
Acquisition Information
This material was received from Roland W. Brown, 1972, 1973, 1974, 1975, 1977, 1978, 1979, and 1980.
Access Terms
University of Wyoming. Summer School;; Jackson Hole (Wyo.)--History--19th Century.; Jackson Hole (Wyo.)--History--20th Century.; Teton Range (Wyo. And Idaho); Teton River Valley (Idaho); Wyoming--History--1890-1918.; Wyoming--History--1919-1945.
Wyoming; Education; Colleges and Universities
Container List
- Biographical material about Roland W. Brown, 1919-1979 (Box 1)
- Audiocassette–Side 1: Biography of Roland W. Brown narrated by himself. Side 2: Brief biography of Carvel W. Brown (brother of Roland) narrated by Roland W. Brown. Carvel Brown then provides an account of an elk hunting trip in Jackson Hole, Wyoming in 1915 with his father, sister, and neighbors, 1974 (Box 3)
- Biographical material about Roland W. Brown’s parents, 1960 (Box 2)
- Roland W. Brown’s travelogues and articles published in Teton Valley newspapers, 1931-1974 (Box 1)
- Tetons- and Teton Valley-related newspaper articles and memorial of Willard Roberts Morgan (1896-1973), first white child born in Alta, Wyoming, 1970-1980 (Box 1)
- Audiocassette with narration by Roland W. Brown about early Alta, Wyoming history and early Teton Valley, Wyoming history, 1973 (Box 3)
- Jackson, Wyoming promotional and history-related materials, 1923-1967 (Box 2)
- Jackson, Wyoming photographs, 1919, undated (Box 1)
- Yellowstone National Park, promotional materials and newspaper articles, 1923-1972 (Box 1)
- Promotional materials about Wyoming tourist destinations, 1919-circa 1920s (Box 2)
- Photocopy of trademark for product made from oil in Salt Creek Oil Field, undated (Box 2)
- University of Wyoming Summer School newspaper articles, bulletins, and memorabilia, 1919-1920 (Box 1)
- Photographic prints: University of Wyoming Summer School trips,Laramie scenes, and Lincoln County (Wyo.) students, 1919-1920 (Box 2)
- Photographic negatives: University of Wyoming Summer School trips,Laramie scenes, and Lincoln County (Wyo.) students, 1919-1920 (Box 4)
- Notice of auto license plate colors to brown and gold to celebrate University of Wyoming's 50th anniversary, 1937 (Box 2)
- Panoramic print: University of Wyoming Summer School class (Roland Brown marked) (access copy duplicate in box 2), 1922; Restricted: Original panoramic photograph in box 5 can be accessed only with an archivist's permission due to fragility. (Box 5 [Restricted])